Andre De Coppet Collection, 1566-1936 (bulk 1770-1865 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (1882-1945), 1919-1936; 1 folder
  - Letters, 1919 September 5-1936 February 7; portion of 1 folder
    - Democratic Executive Committee, 1928; 1 item (Folder 15)
      ALS, New York. Reporting on a conference in Auburn, the success of his campaign for governor in the western upstate region of New York, and bits of business for the committee. Written on Marvin, Hooker & Roosevelt letterhead. 2 pp.
    - Gerlach, Oscar E, 1932 February 26; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Executive Chamber, Albany. Thanking a veteran for his approval and support. 1 p. with original envelope.
    - Hall, Herbert E, 1932 November 5; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Executive Mansion, Albany. Thanking Hall for his support, saying they must first focus on winning the election and then discuss appointments. 1 p.
    - Helmuth, Charles F, 1919 September 5; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Navy Department. Concerning the details of Helmuth's case involving reimbursement for time spent on furlough. Sent by Roosevelt as Assistant Secretary of the Navy. 1 p.
    - Hinsdale, Dr. Guy S, 1931 March 30; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Executive Chamber, Albany. Saying that he cannot go to White Sulphur during the meeting of the Virginia State Bar Association because of his duties as Governor of New York but that he is interested in the fine work being done there. 1 p.
    - Smith, Vernon, 1932 August 27; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Executive Mansion, Albany. Thanking Vernon for sending a newspaper clipping; saying that states must individually consider how to handle the control and distribution of liquor following the repeal of the 18th Amendment. 1 p. with original envelope.
    - Stevens, Mr, 1936 February 7; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TL, Washington. Letter from Roosevelt's private secretary, M.A. LeHand, thanking a Mr. Stevens for his letter and sending a photograph of the President. [The photograph is filed below under Miscellaneous.] 1 p.
  - Miscellaneous, 1933-1936; portion of 1 folder
    - Inaugural Address, 1933; 1 item (Folder 15)
      DS. Printed copy of Roosevelt's inaugural address, given March 4, 1933. Signed on the last page.
    - Photograph, circa 1936; 1 item (Folder 15)
      Signed photograph of Roosevelt sitting at a desk.
    - Caricature, undated; 1 item (Folder 15)
      Signatures of Roosevelt and Herbert Hoover underneath pen and ink caricature portraits of their heads. 1 p.
- Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919), 1877-1918; 3 boxes (1 partial)
  Theodore Roosevelt served as twenty-sixth President of the United States from 1901 to 1909. This series mainly consists of correspondence written by Roosevelt dating from the 1880s until just before his death in 1919. His letters reflect many of the positions he held before being elected President including Civil Service Commissioner under Presidents Harrison and Cleveland and President of the board of New York Police Commissioners. They also frequently touch on his penchant for writing as he corresponded with numerous editors and publishers for works covering everything from politics to hunting. Many of the letters are marked "Personal" and contain Roosevelt's private opinions on official subjects. He responds to criticisms of all kinds, and offers many of his own criticisms, particularly with regards to President Woodrow Wilson's handling of World War I and the treatment of German-Americans. In an 1899 letter to Bartlett S. Johnston, Roosevelt insists he will never be considered for President. The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Miscellaneous documents are housed in a folder at the end.
  - Letters, 1883 November 10-1918 December 19; 2 boxes (1 partial)
    - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1903 January 5-1918 April 26; 1 folder
      Editor of The Outlook.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1903 January 5; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Saying that the Hague Tribunal should act in a certain case, but that having a first-class navy and army are more important. Mentioning the color line in an autograph postscript. 1 p.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1903 February 3; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Discussing in detail various bills before Congress concerning trusts and franchise taxes. 4 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1904 March 14; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Responding to allegations of "White House extravagance," addressing whether the government paid for a new stable, a tennis court, the use of a yacht, the expansion of the White House, etc. Defending his actions and the use of his own money, calling the allegations "fatuous folly." 6 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1907 September 13; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS with autograph additions, Oyster Bay, NY. Marked "Personal." Answering inquiries about the cruise of a navy fleet to the Pacific Coast: the length, number of men, the response should war unexpectedly break out, etc. 3 pp. with original envelope. Also included are transcriptions of two letters from Abbott to Roosevelt (3 additional pages)
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1908 October 1; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Alleging false information and "outrageous bad faith" exhibited in an editorial in The Springfield Republican, which was written in response to a review in Abbott's publication [ The Outlook] concerning the Russo-Japanese Treaty. 2 pp. with original envelope and a newspaper clipping of the offending editorial.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1908 November 14; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS with autograph addition, Washington. Mocking the allegations that Standard Oil controls The Outlook. 2 pp. with original envelope. Also included is a copy of a letter from Abbott to Roosevelt on the same subject. 2 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1909 July 21; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Lake Naivasha (Africa). Referring to fake stories about his hunting exploits in Africa, explaining that he has only hunted for food and for animals to be preserved and given to the National Museum; with mention of [Edward W.] Bok. 2 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1909 October 21; 1 item (Folder 1)
        ALS, Naivasha (Africa). Discussing [Charles] Eliot's list of best books and lambasting [Leo] Tolstoy for hypocrisy and perverted views on marriage; with multiple references to the Russian government. 4 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1911 June 27; 1 item (Folder 1)
        ALS, New York. Saying he hopes Abbott will be away all summer; asking him to give any help possible to the executive committee. 1 p.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1913 November 1; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, Porto Alegre, Brazil. Concerning an article he sent to Abbott on "the Negro in Brazil." Expressing surprise and pleasure at the advanced situation of the Brazilians, with the caveat that they are behind the U.S. in matters of sexual morality. 3 pp.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1916 December 29; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, New York. Saying he cannot write an article proposed by Abbott. 1 p. With a copy of Abbott's letter to Roosevelt requesting the article. 1 p.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1917 January 30; 1 item (Folder 1)
        ALS, Sagamore Hill (NY). Forwarding an article, asking for a proof, and commenting on his bad handwriting. Written on a small card.
      - Abbott, Lawrence F., 1918 April 26; 1 item (Folder 1)
        TLS, New York. Saying that he will not write about the Kaiser and relating a ludicrous story about the Kaiser, the Crown Prince, and himself. 1 p. with a copy of a letter from Abbott to Roosevelt on the same subject. 1 p.
    - Abbott, Lyman, 1906 February 23-1908 August; 1 folder
      - Abbott, Lyman, 1906 February 23; 1 item (Folder 2)
        TLS, Washington. To the editor of The Outlook. Marked "Personal." Responding to an article that was critical of [Henry Cabot] Lodge; defending Lodge and comparing and contrasting him to [Charles] Sumner and [Daniel] Webster. 2 pp. with original envelope.
      - Abbott, Lyman, 1908 August 31; 1 item (Folder 2)
        TLS with autograph additions, Oyster Bay, NY. Responding to a review in The Springfield Republican of a Russian writer's [Prof. Kovalesky] article on the Russo-Japanese Treaty. Describing the true details of his negotiations with both nations and the fact that he only met with them at the request of Japan. A postscript mentions that he is more devoted to seeing [C.E.] Hughes nominated Governor of New York than he was to see [William H.] Taft nominated for President. 2 pp.
    - Allison, John, 1888 June 18-1911 December 27; 1 folder
      - Allison, John, 1888 June 18; 1 item (Folder 3)
        ALS, Oyster Bay, NY. Thanking Allison for information about the Daniel Boone tree which he plans to use in a forthcoming book [ The Winning of the West]. 4 pp.
      - Allison, John, 1911 December 27; 1 item (Folder 3)
        ALS, New York. Making an appointment for Allison to bring his little daughter to visit. 1 p.
    - Badger, Henry C, 1886 April 15; 1 item (Folder 4)
      ALS, Medora, Dakota. On the number of yearlings that can be placed on the range, discussing the price of other cattle. 2 pp. with original envelope.
    - Bigelow, Poultney, 1898 December 2; 1 item (Folder 5)
      TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Hoping to see Bigelow and recalling time together at Santiago. 1 p.
    - Bonaparte, Charles J, 1908 April 8; 1 item (Folder 6)
      TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." To the Attorney General. Telling him to "repair damages" and rest in Baltimore. 1 p.
    - Bridgman, H. A., 1908 February 11-July 20; 1 folder
      - Bridgman, H. A., 1908 February 11; 1 item (Folder 7)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Thanking him for a letter and editorials; saying that the message that he (Roosevelt) wrote was in the spirit of the independent churches who made up Cromwell's army. 1 p.
      - Bridgman, H. A., 1908 July 20; 1 item (Folder 7)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Saying it is impossible for him to commit to write an article for The Congregationalist; hoping he will not be considered churlish for his refusal. 1 p.
    - Buchtel, Henry A, 1908 June 8; 1 item (Folder 8)
      TLS, Washington. To the Governor of Colorado. Announcing the creation of a National Conservation Commission following a suggestion made at a conference of governors. 1 p. With a copy of Roosevelt's order creating the commission. 6 pp.
    - Burbank, Harry E, 1894 March 19; 1 item (Folder 9)
      ALS, Washington. One line: "It is a pleasure to write a line to a gentleman who has been engaged with myself in the endeavour to better the condition of our national civil service." 1 p.
    - Cameron, J. S, 1917 March 21; 1 item (Folder 10)
      TLS, New York. Saying that Panama reserved the right to secede and had ample justification for a revolution. 1 p.
    - Cannon, Joseph G, 1908; 1 item (Folder 11)
      TLS, War Department, Washington. To the Speaker of the House of Representatives. Forwarding a draft of a bill to raise a volunteer army in time of emergency. 2 pp.
    - Carey, R. E, 1901 September 10; 1 item (Folder 12)
      TLS, Buffalo, NY. Thanking him for his letter and saying there is absolute certainty of the President's [William McKinley] recovery. 1 p.
    - Chambers, Julius, 1908 April 25-1918 October 17; 1 folder
      Member of the Lotus Club.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1908 April 25; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Thanking Chambers for a book, telling him to visit when he comes to Washington. 1 p.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1911 August 29; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, New York. "No, Van Wyck did not ask the Rough Riders to parade, nor did he review the regiment. Do let me see you anytime you find convenient." 1 p.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1912 February 3; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, New York. Thanking Chambers for a book, wishing they had more time to visit. 1 p.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1913 August 28; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, New York. Thanking him for sending a newspaper clipping. 1 p.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1914 May 27; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, New York. Hastily thanking him for a letter. 1 p.
      - Chambers, Julius, 1918 October 17; 1 item (Folder 13)
        TLS, New York. Sending his thanks for a favor. 1 p.
    - Charles, Heinrich, 1901 August 26; 1 item (Folder 14)
      TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Thanking him for a letter and advice; introducing Senator [Chauncey M.] Depew. 1 p.
    - Chase, Frederick H, 1915 May 27; 1 item (Folder 15)
      TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Thanking him for a letter. 1 p.
    - Clay, circa 1892 December 1; 1 item (Folder 46)
      ALS, Washington. Responding to suggestions by his editor and providing new content for his book [The Wilderness Hunter], specifically describing the reasons why a bear might walk on two legs. 4 pp.
    - Cleveland, Grover, 1907 March 18; 1 item (Folder 17)
      ALS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Offering congratulations for Cleveland's seventieth birthday. 2 pp.
    - Coudert, Frederic R., Jr, 1901 July 3; 1 item (Folder 18)
      TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Marked "Personal; Not for Publication." Discussing the Philippines and American expansionism, with parallels to other colonial empires. 5 pp.
    - Davis, Anna Agnew, 1900 November 26-1903 July 1; 1 folder
      Mrs. Cushman K. Davis.
      - Davis, Anna Agnew, 1900 November 26; 1 item (Folder 19)
        LS, Albany, NY. Sending sympathy and speaking of his admiration for her husband. 1 p.
      - Davis, Anna Agnew, 1903 July 1; 1 item (Folder 19)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Marked "Personal." Saying that he has written to Mr. Longerman asking for the proposal about the naval station. 1 p.
    - Davis, Cushman K, 1897 December 3; 1 item (Folder 20)
      TLS, Navy Department, Washington. Inviting the senator to a dinner given by the editor of the Sun at which [Henry C.] Lodge and [Garret A.] Hobart will be present; mentioning an allusion to Davis in his book, American Ideals. 2 pp.
    - Denniston, Robert, Jr, 1916 November 3; 1 item (Folder 21)
      TLS, New York. Saying that double the number of Americans have been killed in Mexico and by submarine warfare within the past three and a half years than were killed during the Spanish War. 1 p.
    - Dewey, John F, 1890 June 6; 1 item (Folder 22)
      TLS, Washington. To the Secretary of the Customs Board. "I have to request that you forward at once the reports of examinations held on April 1, 1890." 1 p.
    - Dodge, William E, 1898 December 14; 1 item (Folder 23)
      TLS, New York. Expressing surprise that a Mr. Cassi, who served valiantly in Roosevelt's regiment, has fallen into trouble with General Cesnola. 1 p.
    - Easley, Ralph H., 1917 July 5-1918 December 19; 1 folder
      Secretary of the National Civic Federation.
      - Easley, Ralph H., 1917 July 5; 1 item (Folder 24)
        TLS with autograph corrections, New York. Marked "Private." Harshly stating that Easley must not wholehandedly condemn all Americans of German origin but must judge them by their loyalties, but stating that if any are found to be disloyal to America they should be shot or hanged, specifically mentioning Virieck and two Columbia students. Criticizing President [Woodrow] Wilson. 2 pp.
      - Easley, Ralph H., 1917 July 7; 1 item (Folder 24)
        TLS, New York. Saying that he agrees with Easley about Nagel. Harshly criticizing the government for failing to properly prosecute traitors, with numerous vitriolic statements about President [Woodrow] Wilson. 2 pp.
      - Easley, Ralph H., 1917 August 10; 1 item (Folder 24)
        TLS with autograph corrections, New York. Marked "Private." Continuing his bitter complaints about [Woodrow] Wilson's handling of the war, saying that Wilson is considering his own personal advancement above all else. 2 pp.
      - Easley, Ralph H., 1918 January 23; 1 item (Folder 24)
        TLS, New York. Clarifying misconstrued statements, saying that he has always maintained that the bulk of Americans of German dissent are loyal to America, but that those who are not must be found out and harshly prosecuted. 1 p.
      - Easley, Ralph H., 1918 December 19; 1 item (Folder 24)
        TL, signed by Roosevelt's secretary. Saying that Easley should enlist the help of Harry Lauder and have some wounded veterans speak out against a growing anti-English sentiment in America. Commending Easley on his handling of the "Polish matter." 1 p.
    - Gibson, 1888 December 21; 1 item (Folder 25)
      ALS, Oyster Bay, NY. Asking for assistance in researching early New York, for a volume to be published as part of [E.A.] Freeman's "Historic Towns" series. 2 pp.
    - Gilder, Jeanette L, 1900 November 10; 1 item (Folder 26)
      TLS, Albany, NY. Declining her suggestion to dramatize his book on Cromwell. 1 p.
    - Gilder, Richard Wilson, 1888 May 22; 1 item (Folder 27)
      ALS, Oyster Bay, NY. Saying he is delighted to receive feedback on an article he wrote. Commenting on reference works. 1 p.
    - Goldfogle, Henry M, 1918 October 16; 1 item (Folder 28)
      TLS, New York. Commending Goldfogle on his nomination by the Republicans, saying that his platform of "100% Americanism" stands in stark opposition to the German Socialism of his opponent, Mr. London. 2 pp.
    - Hale, Edward E., 1892 December 6-1901 March 16; 1 folder
      - Hale, Edward E., 1892 December 6; 1 item (Folder 29)
        ALS, Washington. Referring to one of his speeches which Hale has praised, the recent election, and his faith in America. 2 pp.
      - Hale, Edward E., 1901 March 16; 1 item (Folder 29)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Saying he hopes to dine with Hale in Yonkers, expressing admiration for Hale's work. 1 p.
    - Harrison, Frank A., 1911 November 28-1912 January 11; 1 folder
      - Harrison, Frank A., 1911 November 28; 1 item (Folder 30)
        TLS, New York. Saying that books had been sent to the New York Historical Association and that his knowledge of Dutch is limited to one folk song. 1 p.
      - Harrison, Frank A., 1912 January 11; 1 item (Folder 30)
        TLS, New York. Thanking Harrison for sending the text of a Senator's remarks, saying the senator answered a question properly. 1 p.
    - Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1914 November 4; 1 item (Folder 31)
      TLS, New York. Thanking Hart for a book and saying he is strongly advocating the introduction of the Swiss system into the U.S. 1 p.
    - Harvier, Ernest, 1906 October 19-1917 October 2; 1 folder
      - Harvier, Ernest, 1906 October 19; 1 item (Folder 32)
        TLS, Washington. Marked "Personal." Telling Harvier to call on Parsons or [T.L.] Woodruff as the President can do little "in a campaign like this." 1 p. with original envelope.
      - Harvier, Ernest, 1908 October 31; 1 item (Folder 32)
        TLS, Washington. Asking Harvey to call after the election with three gentlemen, mentioning Chaplain Casey. 1 p. with original envelope.
      - Harvier, Ernest, 1908 November 4; 1 item (Folder 32)
        TLS, Washington. Thanking him for his telegram and his contribution to [W.H. Taft's] victory in the election. 1 p. with original envelope.
      - Harvier, Ernest, 1917 October 2; 1 item (Folder 32)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. "Oh, Lord, how I wish I were a sword, or part of the head, and not just one of the writers!" 1 p.
    - Hester, William, 1901 August 20; 1 item (Folder 33)
      TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Refusing to write for the Brooklyn Eagle, as he has refused countless other newspapers and magazines and must remain consistent. 1 p.
    - Johnston, Bartlett S, 1899 November 6; 1 item (Folder 34)
      TLS, Albany, NY. Saying that the party machine would never put him up for President and that his Spanish War record led to his being made Governor. 1 p.
    - King, Horatio C, 1911 June 19; 1 item (Folder 35)
      TLS, New York. Denying the rumor that he is about to join the Scottish Rite, Northern Jurisdiction. 1 p. with original envelope.
    - Lala, Ramon Reyes, 1899 May 25; 1 item (Folder 36)
      TLS, Albany, NY. Commending Lala on the impartiality displayed in his book. 1 p.
    - Long, Mary H. Summer, 1887 December 5-1890 June 11; 1 folder
      - Long, Mary H. Summer, 1887 December 5; 1 item (Folder 37)
        ALS, Oyster Bay, NY. Thanking her for a book, discussing his writing on Robert E. Lee, and offering to send her the next volume of the American Statesmen Series on Gouverneur Morris. 4 pp.
      - Long, Mary H. Summer, 1887 December 14; 1 item (Folder 37)
        ALS, Oyster Bay, NY. Thanking her for a book and letters; commenting on his growing ability to assess men based on facts and less on opinions; declining to write a biography of Jefferson. 4 pp.
      - Long, Mary H. Summer, 1890 June 11; 1 item (Folder 37)
        ALS, Washington. Promising to send a book, commenting on the valor of General [Robert E.] Lee, asking after Colonel Preston. 4 pp.
    - Lord, 1893 July 27; 1 item (Folder 38)
      ALS, Washington. Saying that Lord has not passed his examination for the Patent Office Board. 3 pp.
    - Martin, F. S, 1916 April 20; 1 item (Folder 39)
      TLS, New York. Saying it is a "physical impossibility" for him to accept Martin's invitation. 1 p. with original envelope.
    - McAdoo, William, 1898 April 7; 1 item (Folder 40)
      TLS, Navy Department, Washington. Promising to write to Niblack who is doing admirably abroad. 1 p.
    - McDonough, John T., 1903 August 11-1904 May 18; 1 folder
      - McDonough, John T., 1903 August 11; 1 item (Folder 41)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Concerning the complicated and delicate matter of the disposition of lands owned by the Catholic Church in the Philippines. 2 pp.
      - McDonough, John T., 1904 May 18; 1 item (Folder 41)
        TLS, Washington. Welcoming McDonough home from the Philippines and wishing to see the judge before he makes any public address. 1 p.
    - McDowell, Edward, 1898 November 29; 1 item (Folder 42)
      TLS, New York. Declining an engagement. 1 p.
    - Mingins, George J, 1896 May 12; 1 item (Folder 43)
      TLS, Police Department, New York. Regretfully declining an invitation as Sundays are the only time he can spend with his family. 1 p.
    - Moody, William H., 1902 June 4-1904 April 1; 1 folder
      - Moody, William H., 1902 June 4; 1 item (Folder 44)
        TLS, Washington. "The enclosed memorandum of Admiral Dewey on the general staff seems to me altogether admirable." 1 p. letter with 5 pp. memorandum "Concerning the proposed formation of a general staff for the Navy," signed by George Dewey.
      - Moody, William H., 1902 August 21; 1 item (Folder 44)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. Marked "Personal." Forwarding a letter from the Dean of the University of Chicago [not included], asking if Moody will agree to make the opening address at the campaign in Chicago. 1 p.
      - Moody, William H., 1903 April 26; 1 item (Folder 44)
        TLS, Grand Island, Nebraska. Marked "Personal." Asking Moody to join him for travels through California and Washington State, both for friendship and for the purpose of inspecting navy yards. 1 p.
      - Moody, William H., 1903 April 27; 1 item (Folder 44)
        TLS, Omaha, Nebraska. Marked "Personal." Again asking Moody to join him for travels through California, Oregon, and Washington; promising four days holiday in Yosemite and a rendezvous with Seth Bullock and "a select circle of cowboy friends." 1 p.
      - Moody, William H., 1903 July 7; 1 item (Folder 44)
        TLS, Oyster Bay, NY. "I should like to know what truth there is as regards this story." 1 p. with small newspaper clipping claiming that upwards of 100 American sailors deserted Admiral Cotton in Germany.
      - Moody, William H., 1903 December 5; 1 item (Folder 44)